In this video, I'll be talking about the switch statement.
We'll cover basic usage, case lists, and follow-through behavior.
First, a little bit about switch.
Switch is used to easily check multiple conditions.
And it's an alternative way to do if else blocks.
Switch is execute from top to bottom, and they optionally have a default action.
Let's look at a basic example.
On the left, we have an x, and that's been assigned to the value of 3.
We then use the switch keyword, and we switch on x.
Next, we have the case keyword.
In the case that x is equal to 1, we'll print out 1.
In the case that x is equal to 2, we'll print out 2.
And in the case that x is equal to 3, we'll print out 3.
We then have the default case.
So whenever the case is not covered, instead we'll execute the default.
And the default case for this particular switch is to print out other and the value of x.
It's always a good practice to have a default case, and that's just in the event that you forget to check for a case.
At least you have something that will it be executed.
We're not limited just to switching on integers.
We can also switch on strings.
So around the right, we have a string example.com, and we're switching on this URL variable that we created right here.
So we can do the case of example.com, we'll print out test.
In the case of Google.com, we'll print out live.
And in any other case, so the default case is any other case, we'll print out dev.
We can also have conditional cases.
So in this particular switch statement, we're creating an assigning a variable, and then we're going to switch on it.
So we're creating a variable named result using create an assign.
We're assigning the value of calculate and the function argument of five.
We then use a semicolon, our curly braces, and then within those curly braces, we have our cases.
So our first case will execute when result is greater than 10, our second case will be when our result is equal to six, then this will execute.
And the last case, if the result is less than 10, then this one will execute.
We can also have case lists.
So case lists allows us to check for multiple things in the same case.
So if we switch on x, which would be an integer, on this first case, if it's either one, two, or three, we'll execute some code.
In the second case, if it's 10, 20, or 30, we'll execute this code.
Case lists are useful if you want to take the same action for multiple different values.
The default behavior for switches and go is to automatically stop executing once one of the cases matches.
What this means is if we have a letter and it's a space, then this case does nothing, and none of these will be checked.
However, if we use the fall through keyword, then automatically the next case will be executed.
So for example, if we have the letter be equal to I, this case will be executed because I is present here.
We'll print out a vowel.
The fall through keyword is encountered, and we're going to automatically execute the next case, even though it's not equal to any of these.
So we'll print out a vowel and vowels are great.
The fall through behavior can be useful if you want to always execute some code regardless of which case was matched.
Let's recap.
Switch can be used to easily check a variable for different values.
You can use commas to check multiple values on a single case.
Expressions are also allowed as a case.
You can include function calls, mathematical operations, and logic within these cases.
The fall through keyword will automatically execute the next case, even if it doesn't match.